<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>1588. A sermon preached on the queenes day. Beeing the 17. of Nouember. 1587. at the towne of Lidd in Kent, by Isaac Colfe, preacher of the word of God</title>
            <author>Colfe, Isaac, 1558 or 9-1597.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1588</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 69 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 32 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A19145</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 5552</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S110713</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99846206</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99846206</idno>
            <idno type="VID">11157</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A19145)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 11157)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 204:03)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>1588. A sermon preached on the queenes day. Beeing the 17. of Nouember. 1587. at the towne of Lidd in Kent, by Isaac Colfe, preacher of the word of God</title>
                  <author>Colfe, Isaac, 1558 or 9-1597.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[64] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Iohn Wolfe, for Harry Carre, and are to bee sold at his shop in Pauls Church yard.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1588]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Publication date from STC.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-D (D8 blank).</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  16th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-06</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-08</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-08</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:11157:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:11157:1"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:11157:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>1588.</p>
            <p>A SERMON PREA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>CHED ON THE Queenes day.</p>
            <p>Beeing the 17. of <hi>No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uember.</hi> 1587. <hi>at the</hi> towne of Lidd in Kent, by ISAAC COLFE, Preacher of the word of God.</p>
            <p>LONDON <hi>Printed by Iohn Wolfe,</hi> for Harry Carre, and are to bee ſold at his ſhop in Pauls Church yard.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:11157:3"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:11157:3"/>
            <head>¶ TO MY WORSHIP<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>FVLL FRIENDES, THE Bailife and Iurats of the towne of <hi>Lidd:</hi> Iſaac Colfe <hi>wiſheth all pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperity</hi> in this life, and life euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting in the world to come.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Auing Preached this Sermo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> amon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſt you <hi>(woorſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Sirs)</hi> ſeeing the General wel liking thereof, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withall the deſire of ſome to haue the copy of the ſame: I choſe rather to commit it to the Printer, then to copy it out in writing: becauſe that as the labour ſhould bee eaſier vnto my ſelfe, ſo the benefite ſhould bee greater vnto more. And this I haue done, not vpon the abſolute well ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of the maner of my labour ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, which I confeſſe ſimple: but onely the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſideration of the matter therof
<pb facs="tcp:11157:4"/> which for this time I ſee neceſſary: containing, as appeareth in the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe thereof, the woonderfull ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uauncement of our moſt gratious ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueraigne Q. Elizabeth to the crowne of this Realme, to the ſingular bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fite of vs all: that vpon the conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration therof we might bee the more ſtirred vp to yeeld dutifull thankful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes and prayer vnto God for her: the one in that hee firſt aduaunced her thereunto, and preſerued her hether<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>too therin: the other, that hee would ſtill preſerue and proſper her in the gouernment of the ſame. And I haue thought it requiſite to dedicate this my labour vnto you: not onely be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it was preached amongeſt you: but principally becauſe of thoſe paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing great curteſies which I haue co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually receaued at your hands: For the which as I can not but acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge my ſelfe wholly indebted farre beyond my power fully to requite: ſo do I acknowledge my ſelfe euery way bound to teſtify my thankfulnes vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to you, which is the only recompe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, which either you demaund, or I can
<pb facs="tcp:11157:4"/> geue againe for them. Wherefore vouchſafe, I pray you <hi>Woorſhipfull Sirs,</hi> (as an vndoubted teſtimony therof) to accept this ſame at my hands: who as I am alwaies, and by al waies ready preſt, according to duty, with all the power of body and mynde, to ſeeke your ſpiritual profite: ſo am I as rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy at this preſent, herein to ſatisfy your Godly deſires. The Lord heape vpon you the manifold graces of his holy Spirite in aboundant meaſures, to the benefite of his Church, whereof yee are members: of the Common wealth, whereof yee are ſubiectes: but yet principally of that Corporation, whereof yee are Magiſtrates, to your praiſe on earth, and eternall glory in the higheſt Heauens. At <hi>Lidd.</hi> this firſt of Ianuary. 1587.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your woorſhips to bee commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in the Lord, Iſa. Colfe.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:11157:5"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:11157:5"/>
            <head>A Sermon.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>Text Pſal. 118. verſe. 22. &amp;c.</bibl>
               <q>
                  <p>22 The ſtone which the builders refu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, is the head of the Corner.</p>
                  <p>23 This was the Lords doings, and it is meruailous in our eies.</p>
                  <p>24 This is the day which the Lord hath made: Let vs reioice and be glad in it.</p>
                  <p>25 O Lord I pray thee, ſaue now: O lord I pray thee now geue proſperity.</p>
                  <p>26 Bleſſed is hee that commeth in the name of the Lord, we haue bleſſed you out of the houſe of the Lord.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His Pſalme (woor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipfull and beloued in our Lord and Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour Ieſus Chriſt) was framed by Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid: and that, as it ſée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth, when, after ſo many daungers auoided, he had obtay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned the kingdome of Iudah, &amp; raigned in Hebron. 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 2. And it containeth <note place="margin">2 Sam. 2.</note> partly the wordes of Dauid, exhorting the houſe of Iſrael, the houſe of Aaron, yea and all them which feare the Lord,
<pb facs="tcp:11157:6"/> to praiſe the Lord for his great goodnes and aboundant mercy towardes him: which how great &amp; aboundant it was, hee himſelfe thankfully expreſſeth. And partly the woordes of the people, who vpon the conſideration of the woonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full aduauncement of Dauid, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding all the outragious practiſes of his enemies: and of the happines ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of redounding to their ſingular and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpeakable benefite, with a ſolemne ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruation of the day therof, giue thanks to the Lord therfore: alſo ioyning pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er thereunto for the ſafety and proſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of Dauid their king: to which lat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter part are theſe woords to be referred, which I haue at this preſent hereout, in reſpect of this preſent occaſion through the goodnes of God ſo happily multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyed vnto vs, made eſpeciall choice off to deliuer vnto you: and therefore are to be taken, and vnderſtood, as being the woordes of the people, and not as being the woordes of Dauid.</p>
            <p>They do containe 2 principall partes 1. A declaration of the woonderful and happy aduauncement of Dauid to the kingdome. 2 Theire louing and duti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full
<pb facs="tcp:11157:6"/> behauiour vpon the conſideration thereof.</p>
            <div n="1" type="part">
               <head>The firſt part.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>A declaration of the woonderfull and happy aduauncement of Dauid to the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome.</hi> Wherein yet more particularly y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> people expreſſe firſt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> aduauncement of Dauid <hi>verſe</hi> 22. Secondy how it came to paſſe. <hi>verſe.</hi> 23. Thirdly the benefite therof <hi>verſ.</hi> 24. vntil the middeſt therof.</p>
               <p n="1">1 <hi>The aduauncement of Dauid, verſe. 22. The ſtone which the Buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders refuſed, is the head of the Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner:</hi> For the more liuely deſcribing, and full expreſſing whereof, we ſee, they vſe a metaphor comparing the commune wealth vnto a building: the ſubiectes vnto ſtones therein: the Princes and rulers vnto the builders thereof: the King vnto the head Corner ſtone of the ſame: For albeit that theſe woordes be referred vnto Chriſt: of whom Dauid was a Type and figure, and therefore are ſo vſed by Chriſt. <hi>Math.</hi> 21. And by <note place="margin">Matt. 21. Act. 4.</note> the Apoſtle S. Peeter. <hi>Act.</hi> 4. and elſe where: yet as they were ſpoken by this people in this place, they were applyed vnto Dauid: therby ſhewing that Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid
<pb facs="tcp:11157:7"/> a ſubiect of that Common wealth, although refuſed and perſecuted by the Princes and Rulers thereof, yet was aduau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ced to be King of the ſame, where, Firſt, let vs obſerue the fit vſe of this metaphor by the examination of the partes thereof. Secondly, the applicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on thereof to the purpoſe of the people.</p>
               <p>Firſt concerning the fit vſe of this Metaphor, it is apparant by the parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuler examination of the ſeuerall parts thereof. For euerie Common-wealth is as a building conſiſting of many parts, which being coupled together in one according vnto art, make one houſe: of this houſe firſt euery ſubiect is a ſtone ſeruing in one place or other, and to one vſe or other in the building, whereby as wee learne how perillous in each com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon wealth contention is betweene the ſubiects of the ſame: that it is euen ſuch as if the ſtones of one building ſhould forſake their places &amp; refuſe their offices in keeping in and ſupporting of one another, &amp; ſhould deuide themſelues the one againſt the other, to the beating out and breaking of each other: wherby it muſt needes come to paſſe, that the
<pb facs="tcp:11157:7"/> houſe, yea bee it neuer ſo goodly and ſtately, neuer ſo firme and ſtrong, muſt haue a downfall, and come to deſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: for a houſe deuided againſt it ſelfe can not ſtand, as it is written <hi>Mat. 12.</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Matth. 12.</note>
               </p>
               <p>So hereout wee are taught, with what carefulnes euery one of vs, of what eſtate and condition, of what vocation and calling ſoeuer wee are, ought to procure according to the ſame, the benefite of the Common wealth, whereof we are ſubiects, in that we are borne to be ſtones in this building for the benefite of the ſame: Which <hi>Tully</hi> an heathen oratour <hi>lib. 1, de offic.</hi> could <note place="margin">Cïc. de of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fic. lib. 1.</note> ſée and ſay. <hi>Non nobis ſolum nati ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus &amp;c.</hi> which notable ſaying hee had out of <hi>Plato:</hi> although therefore we are borne partly for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> benefite of our ſelues, partly of our parentes, partly of our friends (yea &amp; of our enemies alſo) yet principally for the benefite of the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon wealth: and ſurely as that ſtone is vnwoorthy to lye on the Earth which will ſerue to no vſe in the building: ſo is that man as vnwoorthy to liue on the earth, which in nothing either can not, or wil not benefite the common wealth.
<pb facs="tcp:11157:8"/> Againe in this houſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> counſailers, no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility, rulers, &amp; al men in authority are builders: whoſe office is, if they ſee this houſe downe, to build it vp, if decaied to repair it: if weakned to ſtrengthen it: if falling to hold it vp: if aſſaulted, to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend it: if ſtrong, for to maintaine it: and this is, firſt, by ordaining of good &amp; hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome lawes according to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> preſent times &amp; occaſions. 2. by the diligent &amp; faithfull execution of them being eſtabliſhed: 3. if néed require, by ſpending their goods &amp; aduenturing their lyues in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> defence of it. Thus ought they to be builders of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> houſe of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Common wealth: otherwiſe well they may beare the name of buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, but they are indeed pluckers down of the ſame. Hee that is not with mee is againſt mee: and hee that gathereth not with mee, hee ſcattereth. <hi>Luc.</hi> 11. there is no middle nor third thing <note place="margin">Luc. 11.</note> betweene the one and the other. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine of this houſe, the King is the head of the Corner, whereby the whole buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding is ſtrengthened and held vp. For as the ſides &amp; quarters of the houſe are ſtrengthened by ioyning vnto the cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners thereof: and as the corners of the
<pb facs="tcp:11157:8"/> houſe being taken away, the houſe can not ſtand, <hi>Iob. cap. 1.</hi> So are all the <note place="margin">Iob. 1.</note> partes and members of the Common wealth ſuſtayned and ſtrengthened by the power of the King, and where there is no King, that Common wealth is like vnto an houſe rent from the cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners thereof, which can not ſtand, but come to confuſion. One notable exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, whereof is to bee ſeene euen in this Common wealth of Iſrael, in the book of the <hi>Iudges:</hi> which albeit, it was directed and gouerned with all good and neceſſary lawes not inuented by man, but ordained by God himſelfe: yet Sampſon beyng dead, there being no Iudge in Iſraell, all thinges came to a miſerable confuſion, as appeareth. <hi>Iudic. 17. 18. 19. 20. 21.</hi> Thus <note place="margin">Iudi. 17. 18. 19. 20. 21.</note> wee ſee how fitly this Metaphor is here vſed in all the partes thereof.</p>
               <p>And now ſecondly followeth the application of the ſame vnto the pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe and meaning of the people, which was thereby to expreſſe the more ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and manifeſtly the aduauncement of Dauid to the kingdome: For this is the profitable vſe of Metaphors, &amp; Alle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gories,
<pb facs="tcp:11157:9"/> parables or ſimilitudes, liuely to deſcribe thoſe thinges, which otherwiſe could not ſo fully be expreſſed. Wherein Firſt, they begin with his reiection, by the builders: Secondly, come to his ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>altation afterwardes.</p>
               <p>Firſt they begin with his reiection, that his exaltation might appeare the more glorious: for the lower the abba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing is, the more notable is the lifting vp: the greater the daunger is, the more woorthy is the victory. <hi>The ſtone which the builders refuſed.</hi> Lo this is the reiection of Dauid. Dauid was a ſtone of the houſe of Iſraell, a ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect of that Common wealth: and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beit, by byrth hee was not great, the ſonne of <hi>Iſhai,</hi> a meane Iſraelite: yet in reſpect of his noble actes, hee was a moſt pretious ſtone, and a principall vpholder of the glory of the ſame, as a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt other thinges moſt euidently appeareth 1. <hi>Samuel</hi> 17. in his encoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tring <note place="margin">1 Sam. 17.</note> with, and ouer comming of Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liah the Philiſtine: for when this Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liah a man of mighty ſtature, and of like ſtrength defied the hoſt of Iſraell, and no man durſt go downe vnto him: this
<pb facs="tcp:11157:9"/> Dauid being yet but of young yeares, and of tender age, yea being alſo vnar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, valiantly encountred with him, and victoriouſly ouercame him, wherby the honor of Iſrael was preſerued, yea and aduaunced: and the enemies van<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſhed &amp; deſtroyed. But what was his reward? <hi>This ſtone the builders refu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed:</hi> They which ſhould haue aduau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ced him, reiected him: yea ſo reiected him, as that they did not onely eſteeme him vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>woorthy to bee the chiefe ſtone of the Corner, but alſo to bee euen an inferi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our ſtone in the building, for they would cleane haue taken him away from the houſe of Iſraell: whereun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to tended all thoſe tyrannous perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutions practiſed againſt him, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of wee read aboundantly in the firſt booke of <hi>Samuel.</hi> Wel, thus wee ſée the reiection of this Stone by the buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders.</p>
               <p>Now followeth his exaltation. <hi>The ſame is the head of the Corner:</hi> al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though the builders refuſed this ſtone, yet y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lord had choſen it, yea &amp; although they had reiected it, yet y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lord had take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it vp, and exalted it: and that not onely
<pb facs="tcp:11157:10"/> to bee a meane ſtone in the building, but euen to bee the head in the Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of the ſame: that is, not onely to be a fellow ſubiect amongſt them in the common wealth, but euen to be king o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer them in the gouernment of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame. Wherby firſt we learn y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> as thoſe things which are highly eſteemed before men, are many tymes abomination in the ſight of God, <hi>Luc. 16.</hi> ſo that on y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> other <note place="margin">Luc. 16.</note> ſide oftentimes thoſe thinges which are reiected of the world, are moſt accepted of God, &amp; that the things which are moſt vile and contemptible before men, are moſt pretious and glorious before God. Dauid, a ſtone refuſed by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> builders, but allowed &amp; choſen of God. 2. Hereout wee learne how impoſſible a thing it is for a man to preuent y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> purpoſe of God: God preuenteth ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in his purpoſes: ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> purpoſeth, but God diſpoſeth al things: but no ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is able to preuent God in his purpoſes: <hi>who ſhal reſiſt his wil?</hi> There <note place="margin">Rom. 9.</note> is neither wiſedeme, vnderſtanding, nor counſaile againſt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lord. <hi>Pro. 21.</hi> For y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Prou. 21.</note> Lord our God is in heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; doth what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer <note place="margin">Pſal. 115.</note> he wil: yea euen notwithſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding all the practiſes of man to preuent him.
<pb facs="tcp:11157:10"/> The Lord had preferred Iacob before Eſau, the younger before y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> elder: Iſaac wold haue preuented it, but the Lord preuented him. Gen. 27. The Lord had <note place="margin">Gen. 27.</note> appointed that Ioſeph ſhould be Lord o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer his brethren, and that his brethren ſhould bowe vnto him and doo him reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence: they would haue preuented it by ſelling him to the Iſmaelites; but the Lord preuented them: they were glad to bowe and crowch before him. <hi>Gen.</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Gen. 42. 43</note> 42. 43. And what néede more examples herein? The Lord had annointed Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid king ouer Iſrael, by the Miniſtry of Samuel. 1. <hi>Sam.</hi> 16. the Princes with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand <note place="margin">1. Sam. 16.</note> it, yea Saule him ſelfe withſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth it: but all in vaine. Dauid is ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uanced to the kingdome of Iudah, and at the length alſo to the kingdome of Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael, as 2. <hi>Sam.</hi> 5. Thus is this ſtone <note place="margin">2. Sam. 5.</note> which the builders refuſed, become the head of the Corner.</p>
               <p>I am not come at this time into this place, worſhipfull and beloued, hiſtori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cally to ſhew vnto you what hath of old come to paſſe vnto Dauid of Iſrael: but chiefly, in conſideration of the daie, by way of application to put you in minde,
<pb facs="tcp:11157:11"/> what hath béen in your own daies done vnto Elizabeth of England. <hi>The ſtone which the Builders refuſed, is the head of the Corner.</hi> Elizabeth that pretious ſtone of the houſe of England refuſed: by whom? by the builders ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of: but what is the euent? the ſame is the head of the corner. Elizabeth refu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, by what meanes? Elizabeth a ſtone of the houſe of England, not of any ſtraunge countrey or forraine nation, and therefore not vnfit: yet had they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſed her: yea Elizabeth a ſtone not of the baſer, but of the moſt pretious ſorte a ſtone of the head corner ſtone, procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding from the loines of the kings of this land: yet had they refuſed her: yea Eli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zabeth a ſtone not ragged but euerie way ſquared, not by the hand of man but by the finger of God, fit for the place and purpoſe, and yet had they refuſed her. And by whome was ſhe refuſed? euen by thoſe which were choſen to be the builders of the houſe of this commo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> wealth: theſe were the Councellers &amp; Nobilitie of this Realme, in the dayes of Queene Mary her ſiſter, who albeit they were the ſworne aſſiſters of the
<pb facs="tcp:11157:11"/> rightfull heire apparant to the Crown of this land: yea, and albeit they knews by ſucceſſion to be heires, and that not by extraordinarie annoynting as the kingdome of Iſrael came to Dauid, but by naturall diſcent from her Father, and confirmed by the laſt will and te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtament of her Father of famous me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morie king Henrie the eight, yet con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarie to law, contrarie to their oth, and contrarie vnto conſcience they refuſed her: and what waies and meanes they deuiſed and put in practiſe not onely to depriue her of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Crown, but alſo of her head whereon the Crown ſhould ſtand, as the hiſtorie therof in the booke of the acts &amp; monuments of the Church recor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded expreſſeth it, &amp; many of you yet ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiently reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber it: ſo it ſhould be néed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe for me now to ſpend any time in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> deliuering of it. Onely therefore this I ſay (which boldly I may ſay) that neuer did Saule &amp; his coherents ſéeke more waies to deſtroy Dauid, then they ſought to deſtroy her: neither was Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid at any time in greater daunger of death being perſecuted by Saul, nor Pe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter in greater perril of beheading being
<pb facs="tcp:11157:12"/> faſt bound in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> priſon by Herod, <hi>Act.</hi> 12 <note place="margin">Act. 12.</note> nor the thrèe children in greater danger of burning when they were in the hotte burning fornace. <hi>Dan.</hi> 3. nor Daniel in <note place="margin">Dan. 3.</note> greater danger of deuouring when hée was in the Lions denne. <hi>Dan.</hi> 6. nor <note place="margin">Dan. 6.</note> Ionas in greater danger of death being alreadie deuoured into the Whales bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſwimming in the midſt of the ſea. <hi>Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nah.</hi> 1. then ſhée was being in the hands <note place="margin">Ionas. 1.</note> of her enemies. But what was the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uent? <hi>The ſame is the head of the Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner:</hi> notwithſtanding all this, her ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies had no power ouer her, they pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uailed not in their purpoſes, but were confounded in their deuiſes: as for Eli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zabeth, ſhe is aduanced to the kingdome, ſhe ſitteth in the throne, ſhe weareth the Crowne, ſhée beareth the Scepter. The ſtone which the builders refuſed, is the head of the Corner: and thus much con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the aduancement of Dauid.</p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>How it came to paſſe.</hi> Now the people expreſſe how it came to paſſe that Dauid was aduanced to the kingdome: how this ſtone being refuſed by the buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, became notwithſtanding the head of the Corner. <hi>verſe. 23. This was the</hi>
                  <pb facs="tcp:11157:12"/> 
                  <hi>Lords dooing, and it is merueilous in our eies.</hi> Where they firſt attribute their working thereof onely to the Lord. Secondly, they confirme it by the mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueilouſnes thereof in their eies.</p>
               <p>Firſt they attribute the aduancement of Dauid to the onely working of the Lord. <hi>It is the firſt doing</hi> and right du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifully: for it is the Lord which hath all things vnder his gouernment and dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction: neither is there any thing done which the Lord hath not done: the leaſt things of this world which we ſée done, are the Lords doing: the holding foorth of our armes, the opening of our lippes, the lifting vp of our eies, nay the fall of the Sparrow, nay the fall of the leafe: or if there be any thing leſſe then the leaſt of theſe, it is the Lords dooing, and ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore how much more the things which are greateſt? Againe in the placing and diſpoſing of the members of the bodie of man, that one member is lower or high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er then another, that the head is higheſt and the foote loweſt, it is the Lords doo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. Againe amongſt thoſe Celeſtiall bodies, that the Sunne is placed aboue Moone and Stars; or (to vſe the words
<pb facs="tcp:11157:13"/> of the Apoſtle. 1. <hi>Cor:</hi> 15.) that there is <note place="margin">1. Cor. 15.</note> one glory of the Sunne, and another of the Moone, &amp; another of the Stars, and that one Starre differeth from another in glory: this is alſo the Lords doing: and ſo likewiſe in the politike body of the common-wealth, that one is aduan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced aboue or below another, before or behind another: that one is the chiefeſt, another the baſeſt, this is alſo the Lords doing: it is the Lord that caſteth downe and exalteth: it is he that raiſeth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> poore out of the duſt, and lifteth vp the begger from the dunghil to ſet him amongſt the princes, that he may inhabite the ſeate of glorie, as Anna confeſſeth in her ſong 1. <hi>Sam.</hi> 2. and as Dauid ſpeaketh, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">1. Sam. 2.</note> 75. Preferment commeth neither from <note place="margin">Pſal. 75.</note> the Eaſt nor from the Weſt, nor from the South, but God is iudge: he maketh low &amp; maketh high: and therefore ſaith the Lord, by the wiſedom of Salomon, <hi>Prou.</hi> 8. By me kings doe raigne: and <note place="margin">Prou. 8. Rom. 13.</note> the Apoſtle, <hi>Rom.</hi> 13. There is no po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer but of God, and the powers that be, are ordained of God: if therefore we ſée any aduanced vnto the ſeat of wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, honor, or maieſtie, yea whether it
<pb facs="tcp:11157:13"/> be by birth, friends, conqueſt, or by any other meanes of man, yet this we muſt acknowledge, that it is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lords doing: For albeit that man was y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> inſtrume<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, yet the Lord is the only author and or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dainer thereof. But yet when this peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple here acknowledge the aduanceme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of Dauid to be the Lords doing, it is af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter a more ſpeciall maner, as it is oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed againſt the doing of man, thereby ſhewing that it was brought to paſſe, only by the power of the Lord, without the helpe, and beyond the expectation of man: for albeit that euen thoſe things which are brought to paſſe by the mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery of man, are ſaid to be done of God, who vſed man as the inſtrument, yet moſt properly are thoſe things ſaid to be the Lords doing which by his abſolute power are brought to paſſe without the helpe &amp; beyond the expectation of man: thus was the deſtruction of Pharao his hoſt, of Senacheribs hoſt, of Herod: and thus wss y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> preſeruation &amp; deliuerance of the Iſraelits, of the thrée children, of Daniel, of Peter, the Lords doing: and thus doe this people affirme y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> aduance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Dauid to be the Lords doing.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:11157:14"/>
               <p>Secondly that it was the Lords doo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, they proue by the marueilouſnes therof. <hi>And it is meruelous in our eies.</hi> As if they had ſaid: Dauid is aduanced to the kingdome, but without the helpe, yea beyond the expectation, yea aboue the reaſon and vnderſtanding of man, yea in ſo ſtrange a maner, as that in our eies it is a thing moſt merueilous: and therefore ſurely it is the Lordes dooing. And was it not a ſtraunge thing &amp; woor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thie to be merueiled at, that Dauid a man of a meane parentage in the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon wealth of Iſraell, the youngeſt of all his brethren, and one fetched from the ſhéepefold, ſhould be annointed to be king? yea &amp; notwithſtanding hee found ſo many enemies, and ſo few friends; ſo many perils, and ſo ſmall ſafetie; being a man reiected and perſecuted by Saul and his princes, yea being a man deſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed and ſcorned of the people, as he him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe ſpeaketh: <hi>Pſal.</hi> 22. Should (Saul <note place="margin">Pſal. 22.</note> being dead, raigne ouer Iudah, and at the length alſo (Iſhboſheth being ſlaine) ouer Iſrael? yet this came to paſſe: Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid that litle one was annointed: that perſecuted and deſpiſed one was aduan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced
<pb facs="tcp:11157:14"/> firſt to be king ouer Iudah: and then alſo ouer Iſraell. <hi>This therefore was the Lords doing, and it is merueilous in our eies.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And no leſſe merueilous, (if we con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider it) was the aduancement of Quéen Elizabeth to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Crowne of this Realme: for what though the kingdome ſucceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiuely by right appertained vnto her? yet if we conſider the multitude and mighti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of her enemies that withſtood her: the infinite number of their ſubtile and deuiliſh deuiſes and practiſes to deſtroy her: again if we conſider the ſmal num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of her able friends to defend her, and her leſſe abilitie to defend her ſelfe: be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a mayden virgine, and therefore vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meete: vnarmed, and therefore vnfit to reſiſt: againe being faſt ſhut within the ſtone walles of ſtrong holdes, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore not able to fly, but enforced to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenture the extremitie of thoſe dangers which by her bloudie enemies were dai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly threatned againſt her, and prepared for her: againe on the other ſide, if wée conſider how ſodenly and wonderfully the chiefeſt of her enemies, when ſhée was in chiefeſt danger of death, and in
<pb facs="tcp:11157:15"/> the iudgement of man in deſperate e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate of life, were brought to deſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: wherby (Quéene Mary being dead) ſhe was aduanced to the Crowne: I ſay if we throughly co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſider theſe things, and accordingly waigh them in the true ballances of an vpright mind, we ſhall find the aduancement of Quéene Eliza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beth, a thing moſt marueilous in our eyes: yea and the more we conſider it, the more marueilous we ſhall find it: yea &amp; I aſſure my ſelfe, &amp; you (dearely beloued) that of all thoſe marueilous works which through the mighty hand &amp; outſtretched arme of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lord, we haue either with our eyes ſéene in our daies, or els with our eares heard in the daies of our fathers to haue come to paſſe, this one is the greateſt &amp; the moſt meruei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous in the eyes of all thoſe which throughly and vprightly conſider it, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen this, the aduancement of Quéene Elizabeth to the Crowne of this land: It was maruailous in the eyes of her verie enimies, who were amaſed at the ſight of it, and whoſe hearts are yet a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoniſhed at the remembrance of it: if therefore it ſéeme not marueilous in the
<pb facs="tcp:11157:15"/> eyes of any, it is in the eyes of thoſe which conſider it not. Wherefore if we are not too ſottiſh, we can not but ſée, and too malicious, we can not but ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge that it is the Lords doing, and not mans: that it is the Lord which hath pleaded her cauſe, and reuenged her wrong, and that he onely which is mightie and almightie hath magnified her, ſaying: It is the Lords doing, and it is marueilous in our eyes.</p>
               <p n="3">3 <hi>The benefit thereof.</hi> After that the people haue expreſſed the wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulnes of Dauids aduancement, they likewiſe expreſſe the benefit thereof, <hi>Verſ. 24. This is the day which the Lord hath made,</hi> euen to the ſinguler benefit of the whole Common-wealth. For here they ſpeake of a ſpeciall day made by God vnto a ſpeciall vſe: for otherwiſe there is no day which the Lord hath not made, and that euen for the vſe of man: as appeareth <hi>Geneſ.</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Gen. 1.</note> 1. The Lorde made the light, and deuiding it from the darkeneſſe, cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the light, Day, and the darke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, Night, and ſo hee made the firſt, ſecond, third, fourth, fift,
<pb facs="tcp:11157:16"/> and ſixt, in which hee made the world and all the creatures therein: and the ſeuenth, wherein he reſted from all his <note place="margin">Gen. 2.</note> worke which hee had made, and ſo hee likewiſe maketh euerie day vnto the end of the worlde: for as now and alwaies in his prouidence hee appointeth what thinges in euerie day from day to day ſhall be done; ſo hee alſo in the ſame his prouidence, maketh euerie day wherein all things ſhalbe done. Here therefore, as I ſaid before, they ſpeake of a ſpecial day made of God vnto a ſpeciall vſe for the ſame people: and that not of a ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall day made for the ſending of a ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all plague (for thus alſo is the day of tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bulation and of affliction for the puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the ſinnes of the vngodly, a ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall day which the Lord hath made to a ſpeciall vſe: and therefore the day ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed for the captiuitie and deſtruction of the Iewes, <hi>Ierem. 30. Ioel. 1. Amos. 5. Zophon.</hi> 1. is called the day of the <note place="margin">Ierem. 30. Ioel. 1. Amos. 5. Zophon. 1.</note> Lord,) but of a ſpeciall day made by him to their ſpeciall benefit and commoditie: this day was the day of the aduanceme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of Dauid vnto the kingdome, whereby the whole common wealth after the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happie
<pb facs="tcp:11157:16"/> raign, and happie death of Saul, was wonderfully bleſſed: and therefore ſay they, this day the Lord hath made, not to the benefit of one, or a fewe, but to the benefite of the whole common wealth. The Lord had made many daies for the benefite of that people before the time of Dauid both in the time of Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, and of Ioſua, and of the Iudges, and of Samuel, as appeareth in the peruſing of thoſe bookes: but yet amongſt thoſe there was not one, wherein they had re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued greater bleſſings, then in this day of the aduancement of Dauid: and how greatly they were bleſſed thereby, hée that peruſeth <hi>lib.</hi> 2. of <hi>Sam.</hi> and <hi>lib.</hi> 1. of the <hi>Chronicles,</hi> ſhall finde the ſame moſt truely recorded, and fully diſcour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed: and whereas infinitely they were bleſſed thereby, yet the bleſſednes conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted principally in two things: firſt in his happie victories to the ſubduing of his enemies, whereby his ſubiects were preſerued in peace, and mainteined in proſperitie. Secondly, in his feruent zeale to religion, whereby his people vnder him were trained vp in the true ſeruice of God, and therefore worthely
<pb facs="tcp:11157:17"/> doe they acknowledge <hi>This daye the Lord hath made.</hi> Now as this peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple ſpeaking of the day of the aduance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of Dauid to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> kingdom of Iudah, acknowledge the ſame to bee a ſpeciall day wherin the Lord had ſhewed mercy vnto them, in pouring out his bleſſings vpon them: ſo likewiſe haue we (dearely beloued) the people of this lande as great cauſe vpon the conſideratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the aduancement of Quéene Elizabeth to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Throne therof, to acknowledge the day thereof, a ſpecial day ordained of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lord our God for the ſinguler benefit of the ſame: ſaying with this people, <hi>This is the day which the Lord hath made.</hi> I might expreſſe the bleſſed eſtate of this land, by conferring the ſame vnder her maieſties gouernment, with the eſtate of Iudah &amp; Iſrael, vnder y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> gouernment of Dauid, of olde: or I might expreſſe it by conferring the eſtate therof with the eſtate of other nations round about vs, &amp; bordering vpon vs at this day, either of which might eaſily proue it vnto vs: but that I might not ſéeme <hi>nimis curio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus in aliena Republica,</hi> I will make it manifeſt by conferring it with it ſelfe.
<pb facs="tcp:11157:17"/> The eſtate of it now with the eſtate of it in times paſt: neither do I meane to this end, to call backe the conſideration of the eſtate thereof in the dayes of her Progenitors whom we knew not: but onely to examine it, by conferring the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate thereof now with the eſtate of the ſame in the dayes of Quéene Mary her ſiſter, whom as you, for the moſt part know, ſo what the eſtate of the Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon wealth was vnder her, you for the moſt part can not but remember: that hauing conferred things together which you haue known, and had full experience of, you might the better iudge betwéen the one and the other: here therefore if we conſider how it was gouerned &amp; left by the on<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e, and how it hath béene maintai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned &amp; gouerned by the other, the benefit of this day of the aduanceme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of Quéen Elizabeth to the Crowne of this land, ſhall moſt clearely ſhine, &amp; fully be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed vnto vs. Quéene Mary left it vexed with the inſolency of the Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh nation whom ſhe brought in. Quéene Elizabeth hath eaſed it, Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry left it in warre, Elizabeth hath gouerned it in peace: Mary left it
<pb facs="tcp:11157:18"/> in debt, Elizabeth hath diſcharged it: Mary left it in pouertie, Elizabeth hath enriched it: Mary left it weake, Eliza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beth hath ſtrengthned it: nay further, (wherein the perfection of our preſent happines conſiſteth) Mary baniſhed true religion, Elizabeth hath reſtored it: Mary perſecuted it, Elizabeth hath defended it: Mary caſt it downe, Elizabeth hath aduanced it. Mary with the intollerable ſuperſtitions of Antechriſt, defiled it, Elizabeth by caſting them out, hath purged it: ſo that now with liberty of body we enioy frée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of conſcience, in ſtead of being ſtrangers in other lands, our land is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come a ſafe receptance for the godly per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecuted of other natio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s: as in worldly, ſo in all ſpirituall bleſſings we are won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfully enriched: briefely, we all of vs more fully féele the bleſſednes of our e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate, then any tongue, much leſſe mine, is able to expreſſe. If therefore the Lord euer made any day for the benefit of Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael, yea or any day for the benefit of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny nation vnder the heauens, then euen this day of the aduancement of Quéene Elizabeth to the kingdom of England
<pb facs="tcp:11157:18"/> hath the Lord made for the vnſpeakable happines of the ſame. Happy did En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland thinke it ſelfe in the dayes of King Henry hir noble father: happy did it think it ſelfe in the dayes of king Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward her godly brother: but yet neuer could it repute it ſelfe ſo happy, as it hath bene during the raigne of victori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Queene Elyzabeth: ſo vnſpeakable an happy day was this, of the aduaunce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Queene Elizabeth: and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore how ſhal we but acknowledge this day made &amp; appointed of the Lord our God for the happines of England? ſure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly neuer did the Lord make any ſuch day before it, neither will he euer make any ſuch day after for the happines of England. The Lord therefore vouch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſafe to lengthen this day, not onely as the day of Ioſuah, but euen as the daies of Heauen and Earth. And thus much concerning the firſt part, containing the declaration of the woonderfull and hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py aduauncement of Dauid to the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="part">
               <head>The ſecond part.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>The louing and dutifull behauiour of the</hi>
                  <pb facs="tcp:11157:19"/> 
                  <hi>people vpon the conſideration thereof.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Which conſiſteth in 3. things: firſt, in a reioycing, <hi>verſ.</hi> 24. ſecondly, in a prayer, <hi>verſe</hi> 25. thirdly, in a bleſſing, <hi>verſe</hi> 26.</p>
               <p n="1">1 <hi>A reioycing,</hi> which is vttered by way of mutuall exhortation, ſtirring vp one another vnto the ſame, <hi>verſe. 24. Let vs reioice, &amp; be glad in it.</hi> Which is the louing nature of Gods children towards their brethren: if they ſee and know themſelues to bee ſuch as they ſhould bee, they enuy not thoſe that bee like vnto them, but rather wiſh and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire that they all were ſuch as they the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues are: ſo <hi>Paul. Act.</hi> 26. aſſuring him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe <note place="margin">Act. 26.</note> vnfainedly to ſerue the Lord, wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſheth that not onely <hi>Agrippa,</hi> but alſo all they which heard him ſpeak that day were altogether ſuch as hee himſelfe was, onely his bandes excepted: &amp; ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore in al godly actions which they duti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully exerciſe, not ſatiſfying themſelues with their owne diligence, they alſo ſtir vp one another by exhortation to ioine with them in them according to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent occaſion offered: as if occaſion bee offered to heare the word preached, they ſtirre them vp vnto hearing with them:
<pb facs="tcp:11157:19"/> if to exerciſe themſelues in prayer, to pray with them: if in faſting, to faſt with them: if in lamentation, to lame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t with them: briefly, if in reioycing, to reioyce with them: as the people in this place, hauing occaſion of ioy and reioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing geuen vnto them by the aduaunce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of Dauid, exhort each others there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto, ſaying: <hi>Let vs reioyce and bee glad.</hi> In which their reioycing, yet more particularly we are to obſerue 3. things: firſt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> perſons who are exhorted of one another to reioice. <hi>Let vs:</hi> ſecond<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the tyme when. <hi>In it:</hi> y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is, in this day which the Lord hath made: thirdly, what maner of reioycing it ſhould bee.</p>
               <p>Firſt concerning the perſons who are exhorted by each other to reioyce, they are, wee. <hi>Let vs</hi> reioyce and bee glad. Albeit, that ſo great happines came to that common wealth, by the aduaunce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Dauid to the kingdome: yet notwithſtanding all reioyced, not there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>at, neither were glad thereof: but many no doubt, of the fooliſh people which knew not what was good for them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues inwardly, greeued thereat, yea and many wee know ſtormed at the
<pb facs="tcp:11157:20" rendition="simple:additions"/> ſame, and laboured what in them lay to depoſe Dauid from his Throne, and to depriue him of his Crowne: of theſe was Abner y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> chiefe Captaine of Sauls hoſt the chiefe, who ſeeing Dauid now raigne in Hebron ouer Iudah, tooke Iſhboſheth Sauls ſonne, and made him king ouer Iſrael. 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 2. This, know <note place="margin">2. Sam. 2.</note> this people, the thing was notorious amongſt them: &amp; yet comfortably they ſay one to another, <hi>Let vs reioice and be glad:</hi> as if they had ſaid to each other what though many of the fooliſh people greeue at the aduaunceme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of our king Dauid: yea and what though rebelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Abner &amp; his confederats of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> houſe of Saule ſtorme thereat, and by the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uauncement of Iſhboſheth to y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> crowne of Iſrael, do not onely labour to keepe him backe from the Crowne of Iſraell, which yet hee hath not, but alſo to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe him from the Crowne of Iudah, which hee now enioyeth, yet as for vs <hi>Let vs</hi> reioice and be glad of it. In like ſort, notwithſtanding the great and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpeakable happines of this Common wealth by the aduauncenent of Queene Elizabeth to the crowne thereof, yet all
<pb facs="tcp:11157:20" rendition="simple:additions"/> reioyced not thereat, neither haue they bene glad thereof: but many no doubt of the fooliſh &amp; ſuperſtitious people haue greeued at it: yea and many rebellious ones, we know by inſurrections open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and by conſpiracies ſecretly, haue la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boured what in them lay, &amp; baue aduen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tured there liues to depriue her of it, but yet notwithſtanding (dearly beloued) as for vs, let not their fooliſhnes beſotte vs, but let vs reioice, and bee glad thereof: yea euen ſo many of vs (which I hope is all of vs) as haue a loue to the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent proſperity of the Church of Chriſt amongſt vs, or a loue to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> preſent peace and happines of this common wealth: yea or a loue to the preſent welfare of our ſelues, let vs reioice and bee glad: for euen all theſe thinges, next vnder God, ſpring herefrom: eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> from the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uauncement of Queene Elizabeth.</p>
               <p>Secondly, concerning the time of this reioicing, let vs (ſay they) reioyce and bee glad <hi>In it:</hi> that is in this day which the Lord hath made for the aduaunce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Dauid. Whereby we ſee that this people ſolemnly obſerued and kept the day of the aduauncement of Dauid
<pb facs="tcp:11157:21"/> to the kingdome of Iudah: which not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding is not that obſeruation of dayes diſſliked and reiected by the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle Saint Paule <hi>Gal. 4. &amp; Coloſſ.</hi> 2. <note place="margin">Gal. 4. Col. 2.</note> where only the ſuperſtitious obſeruati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of daies and times are condemned: but religiouſly to obſerue thoſe dayes wherein the Lord hath done principall thinges either for the benefitte of his Church whether generall or particular amongeſt vs: or for the benefite of the common wealth wherein wée liue, as I finde neither co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundement, nor coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaile, nor example to condemne it, ſo finde I manifold examples not amon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſt the Heathen people recorded by prophane writers (which I willingly omit): but amongeſt the people of God themſelues, ſet downe in the holy ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures (which I can not ouerſlip.) What dayes the people of Iſraell were com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunded to keepe holy vnto the Lorde you may reade, <hi>Deut.</hi> 16. and els where <note place="margin">Deut. 16.</note> euen the dayes of the Paſſeouer of Pe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tecoſt, Tabernacles and ſome others, in remembrance of thoſe great bleſſinges, which they had receiued at the hands of the Lord. Againe, when by the meanes
<pb facs="tcp:11157:21"/> of Quéene Heſter, the Iewes vnder A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haſhueroſh were preſerued from the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction practiſed againſt them by Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, and hauing ouerthrowen their e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies had gotten reſt, and were in ſaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty: ſhée by the aduiſe of hir godly vncle Mardocheus gaue co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundement vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the whole people of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Iewes through out all the prouinces of the king Aha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhueroſh, that they ſhould euery yeare keepe the xiiii. and xv. daies of the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth Adar holy, in reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>brance of their woonderfull deliuerance. <hi>Eſter.</hi> 9. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine <note place="margin">Eſter. 9.</note> when the ſame people by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> means of Simon the high prieſt, had bene deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered from the tyranny of Tryphon. Simon ordained that the ſame day: e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen the 23. day of the ſecond moneth ſhould bee kept euery yeare with glad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes: 1. <hi>Mac.</hi> 13. and what neede more <note place="margin">1 Mac. 13.</note> examples? This people here ſeeing Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid aduaunced to the kingdome of Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dah, as a day wherein they had recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued ſo great a bleſſing at the handes of the Lord, they ſolemnely obſerue the ſame, and that with reioycing, ſaying: this is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> day which the Lord hath made: let vs reioyce and be glad <hi>In it.</hi> If euer
<pb facs="tcp:11157:22" rendition="simple:additions"/> the people of Iſraell had any iuſt cauſe to obſerue with reioycing any day in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance ether of any euill auoided, or of any benefite receiued at the handes of the Lord: yea, or if any people vnder the heauens hath had at any time iuſt occaſion to do the ſame: ſurely the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> haue wee euen the people of this Common wealth, as great cauſe as they that haue had the greateſt, whether in reſpect of the one, or in reſpect of the other, ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemnely with reioycing to obſerue this day, wherein wee now breath, the 17. of Nouember: which is the day of the memorial of the beginning of the happy raigne of our moſt gracious ſoueraigne Queene Elizabeth ouer this land: for on this day, now 29. yeares it was, that the Lord in mercy remembring vs whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> we litle hoped, and leſſe deſerued, by ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king away of Queene Mary, aduaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced Queene Elizabeth ouer vs: where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by what plagues wee were deliuered from, and what bleſſednes wee reaped, you heard before in part, but can not fully bee expreſſed: wherefore now in this day let vs reioyce and be glad, yea, and although euery day ought to be vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
<pb facs="tcp:11157:22"/> vs a day of reioicing therat: yet prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipally we ought to reioyce in this day. How can wee but euery day reioyce thereat, when as euery day wee reape the benefite thereof? There doth not one day throughout the yeare, nay throughout y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> whole courſe of our liues, paſſe ouer our heads, but that therein euery one of vs, high and low, rich and poore, young and old, do many wayes both ſee in others, and feele in our ſelues the vnſpeakable benefits of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> aduaunce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Queene Elizabeth: and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore euery day ought to be vnto vs a day of reioycing: euery day haue wee iuſt cauſe to fall downe on our knees, and geue God thankes for Elizabeth: but yet principally wee ought to reioyce in this day, which now wee ſolemnly ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue in memoriall thereof, for that this is the end wherfore all ſuch ſolemne ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruation of ſpecial dayes for ſpecial be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefites haue bene ordayned and vſed: e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen that they ſhould be beſtowed in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioycing: not in faſting: but in feaſting, not in weeping, but in reioycing: wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore principally in this day we ought to reioyce for y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> aduauncement of Queene
<pb facs="tcp:11157:23"/> Elizabeth. Therefore, <hi>Let vs reioice and be glad in it.</hi> Let not our ſo long enioying of her, ſlacke our ioy, or quaile our reioucing for her: but rather as the longer wee enioy her, the more wee are bleſſed by her: ſo haue wee euery yeare renuing of this day, the greater cauſe to reioyce for her, and therefore euen in this day let vs reioyce and bee glad thereof: yea euery way let vs teſtify vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the whole world this our reioycing: let the cherefulnes of our cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tenances, the decency of our garmentes, the ſongs of our lippes, the clapping of our hands, our melody on inſtruments of muſicke, the making of bonefires, the ringing of belles, the ſounding of trum pettes, the diſplaying of banners, the ſhooting of gunnes: yea, and whatſoeuer meanes haue bene vſed, or may bee deuiſed as teſtimonies of reioycing, let them be v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed of vs as an euident teſtimony of our vnfayned and harty reioycing this day, for the aduaunceme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of Queene Eliza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beth.</p>
               <p>Thirdly concerning the maner of this our reioycing, it muſt alſo bee obſerued: for there is areioycing which is euil, as
<pb facs="tcp:11157:23"/> the Apoſtle ſpeaketh. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5. The end of which is, weeping: as Chriſt teſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth <note place="margin">1 Cor. 5. Luc. 6.</note> 
                  <hi>Luc.</hi> 6. woe be vnto you which now laugh and reioyce: for yee ſhall wayle and weepe. This our reioycing there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore muſt be onely in the Lord: in the ſame wee muſt not forget God: which fault man for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> moſt part falleth into in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> middeſt of his reioycing: in his reioy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cing he is ſo ouerioyed, as y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he clean for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>getteth to reioice in him in whom hee ought to reioyce: the reioycing in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> gift, maketh him forgetfull to reioyce in the geuer: if God geue wealth, health of bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy after pouerty and ſicknes: ſtrength after weaknes, peace after war, plen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty after ſcarcity, &amp;c. euery man is glad thereof and reioyceth thereat. But who is hee that reioyceth in him, who hath beſtowed thoſe thinges on him? the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of Iſraell beyng brought out of E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gypt from the ſlauery of Pharao, and of the Egiptians, they were, no doubt glad thereof and reioyced therat, but as Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid ſpeaketh, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 106. They forgat <note place="margin">Pſal. 106.</note> God their Sauiour which had done great things in the land of Egipt, won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derous woorks in the land of Ham, and
<pb facs="tcp:11157:24"/> fearefull thinges in the red ſea for them: ſo thoſe ten Leapors ſpoken of in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell, <hi>Luc.</hi> 17. beying healed of their le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proſie <note place="margin">Luc. 17.</note> by Chriſt, were all, no doubt, full glad thereof, and reioiced: but yet all forgate to reioyce in him who had ſhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wed this mercy vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: for onely one of them (who was a Samaritane) re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned backe, falling downs on his face gaue him thankes, and with a lowde voice gaue praiſe vnto God. Of al thoſe bleſſinges, which wee the people of this nation at this preſent enioy, or euer in times paſt haue enioyed: this one, euen the aduaunceme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of Queene Elizabeth ouer this land is not the leaſt but rather the greateſt, and therefore not the leaſt, but the moſt woorthy to bee reioyced at of al of vs which reape the benefite ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of: but yet in this our reioicing we muſt bee mindfull to reioice in him who hath geuen Elizabeth vnto vs, and aduaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced her ouer vs: For this was the Lordes doing and not mans, but euen without the helpe of man, yea euen be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yonde the expectation of all men: nay further, contrary to the wil of the chie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt men of this world, as you heard be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore,
<pb facs="tcp:11157:24"/> the Lord brought it to paſſe: in who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> therefore ſhould we reioyce but in him? for in whom ſhould wee reioyce but in him who hath bene the woorker thereof? hee onely is woorthy of the praiſe, who alone hath done the worke: yea and to this end it is, that hee hath ſo miracu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſly brought the ſame to paſſe, that no fleſh ſhould reioyce in his preſence: but that hee which reioyceth, ſhould reioice in him: ſaying: Not vnto vs, O Lord, not vnto vs, but vnto thy name geue y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> praiſe, for thy louing mercy and for thy truthes ſake, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 126. Let this our re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioycing <note place="margin">Pſal. 126.</note> teſtify our thankefulnes vnto him for the ſame: Wee are not woorthy of the leaſt of all his mercies, <hi>Gen.</hi> 32. <note place="margin">Gen. 33.</note> much leſſe of this: and all which wee haue, or can geue vnto the Lord our God is not woorthy the name of a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compence for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> leaſt, much leſſe for this: &amp; yet ſuch is the mercy of our God vnto our weaknes, as that this onely hee re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quireth at our handes for al his vnſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kable benefits in ſo ouerflowing a mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure powred vpon vs, euen this, that we ſhould geue thankes vnto him: and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioice in his holy name: therefore Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid
<pb facs="tcp:11157:25"/> vpon the conſideration of the woon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfull mercies of God towardes him, falling into this godly meditatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: what ſhall I render vnto the Lord for all his benefites beſtowed vpon mee? <hi>Pſal.</hi> 116 <note place="margin">Pſal. 116.</note> thereby acknowledging that hee was both altogether vnwoorthy of them: &amp; all which hee could geue was no pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portionall recompence for them, and at the length reſoluing himſelfe what re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compence to geue, breaketh foorth into theſe woords. I wil take the cup of ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation, and will call on the name of the Lord: Loe then, this one payment doth fully ſatiſfy the Lord for all his graces, benefites, and bleſſings powred vpon vs: And therefore alſo for this. O therefore that we could truly reioyce in him, and hartely be thankfull vnto him this day, and euen for Elizabeth: that the Lord may this day and euer bleſſe vs with Elizabeth: God forbid y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> our vnthankfulnes vnto him ſhould bereaue and depriue vs of Elizabeth, &amp; of this ſo great happines which we haue ſo long time enioyed, and now at this preſent do, and long time hereafter may (which God grant) enioy by Elizabeth:
<pb facs="tcp:11157:25"/> as therfore this day the Lord hath made for our ſingular benefite and vnſpeaka<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble happines: ſo let vs reioyce and bee gladde in it, and beſtow the ſame in thankſgeuing vnto him for the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uauncement of Elizabeth.</p>
               <p n="2">2 <hi>A Prayier,</hi> from reioycing they come vnto prayer. <hi>Non minor eſt vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus quam quarere, parta tueri:</hi> as Dauid could not without the helpe of the Lord obtaine the kingdome: ſo nether could he without the helpe of the Lord defend himſelfe and gouerne it: and therefore as they ſaw iuſt occaſion to reioyce in him for the one, ſo they ſaw as iuſt occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion to pray vnto him for the other, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>verſe. 25. O Lord I pray thee ſaue now: O Lord I pray thee now geue proſperitie.</hi> Where wee ſay they pray for two thinges in the behalfe of Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid the King: firſt <hi>Saluation,</hi> ſecondly <hi>Proſperity.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Firſt they pray for <hi>Saluation. O Lord I pray thee ſaue now,</hi> that is, from the hand of the enemy which la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boureth to ſupplant him: In the time of mirth they remembred eminent daun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers, they thought of perils at hand:
<pb facs="tcp:11157:26"/> which the Preacher <hi>Cap.</hi> 11. exhorteth <note place="margin">Eccl. 11.</note> vs vnto: though a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> liue many years, and in them all reioyce, yet let him re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member the dayes of darknes, that is, of affliction and trouble. There is no mans eſtate in this world ſo quiet, but y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> it is mixed with many troubles, nor ſo ſafe, but y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> it is ſubiect to many dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers: but yet principally the eſtate of a King, it is moſt troubleſome and peril<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous. And therfore they knew that Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid beeing now aduau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ced to the throne of the kingdome of Iudah, and that in ſuch maner as before is declared, could not but finde many enemies, by whom he ſhould bée ſubiect to no few troubles, nor ſmall daungers, yea &amp; many were the troubles and perils which were laid before him, and ſtirred vp againſt him, of his deſperate enemies both within &amp; without, both for his aduauncement to Iudah and Iſraell: within beyng ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaunced to the kingdome of Iudah: he had thoſe that ſtriued for the aduaunce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Iſhboſheth Sauls Sonne: and theſe were they of the houſe of Saule, of whom you heard before: betweene whom there was a long warre, as ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peareth,
<pb facs="tcp:11157:26"/> 2. <hi>Sam.</hi> 3. beyng aduaunced to <note place="margin">2 Sam. 3.</note> the kingdome of Iſraell: both within and without viewing him, within: firſt his owne ſonne Abſalon: the She<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ba the ſonne of Bechin, a man of Iemini: both which rayſed vp Iſrael againſt Dauid: without, he had the Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſtines and other nations oft times ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king war vpon him of both which you may read ple<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tifully. 2. <hi>Sam.</hi> 5. wherfore <note place="margin">2. Sam. 5.</note> they ſéeing Dauid ſubiect to ſo many pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rils, they pray for ſaluatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> at the hands of God, ſaying, <hi>O Lord I pray thee ſaue now:</hi> For what was Dauid a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt his aduerſaries? either in multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude or mightines? wherefore they flye vnto the Lord for refuge and defence: ſaue now, O Lord, eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thyne annoyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted whom thou haſt aduaunced from the handes of his enemies, which purpoſe and practiſe his deſtruction.</p>
               <p>Secondly, they pray for the proſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of their king: <hi>O Lord I pray thee now geue proſperity:</hi> as Dauid could not ſaue himſelfe from the hands of his enemies, except the Lord ſaued him: ſo neither could hee gouerne the common wealth, except the Lord proſpered him
<pb facs="tcp:11157:27"/> therin: It is no eaſy thing to gouerne a kingdome: &amp; to order a common wealth, for the welfare &amp; happines of the people: if the Lord teach not y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> king what to doo, by whom ſhal he be directed? If y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lord direct him not, how ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he proſper in any thing which he taketh in hand? how ſhal he proſper in his counſails? how ſhal he proſper in his enterpriſes? If the Lord build not the houſe, in vaine do they la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour that build it. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 127. They euen <note place="margin">Pſal. 127. Gen. 11.</note> with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſons of men, <hi>Gen.</hi> 11. thinke they to build neuer ſo lofty a building, yet they build vnto themſelues nothing elſe but a Tower of confuſion: The com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon wealth can not proſper, but come to ruine and deſtruction: wherefore O Lord I pray thee geue now proſperity vnto Dauid our King: that thou proſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pering him, the Common wealth may bee in proſperity by him. The exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of this people (dearly beleued) tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth vs that in the middeſt of this our reioycing this day for the happy ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uauncement of our moſt gratious So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueraigne, Queene Elizabeth, we muſt not forget to ioyne prayer therunto for her, euen for the ſafety and proſperity
<pb facs="tcp:11157:27"/> of Elizabeth: ſaying, <hi>O Lord I pray thee, &amp;c.</hi> Firſt for her ſafety, and that from the handes of her enemies: for al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beit that ſhe is aduaunced to the throne of the kingdome, yet hath ſhée not bene neither is ſhee frée from her mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold perils: firſt by her rebellious ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iectes within, who for the aduaunceme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of an Iſhboſheth, nay of a Iezabell to the Crowne, both by open inſurrecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, leuying of armies, diſplaying of Banners, and pitching of fieldes: and alſo by ſecret conſpiracies, with dagges and daggers, &amp;c. haue practiſed her de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction: then by forraine enemies of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther nations: for we are not ignorant of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> often thretned inuaſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s in times paſt: neither can we be ignorant of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> purpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed &amp; prepared miſchiefe at this preſent to depoſe her from the Crown. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, <hi>O Lord I pray thee ſaue now,</hi> e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen thyne annoynted: thou which haſt lifted her vp, hold her vp, that thine and her enemies plucke not her downe who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thou haſt exalted: continue thy wonted goodnes towardes her, as thou haſt he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therto ſaued her, ſo ſaue her now: make perfect that ſame good woorke which
<pb facs="tcp:11157:28"/> thou haſt begunne in her: yea, <hi>Now,</hi> O Lord ſaue her: for now is the wrathful indignation of thine and her enemies, as a conſuming fire enflamed againſt her: wherefore, O Lord, ſaue now, yea and ſaue her for euer. Hereunto wee muſt ioyne prayer for her proſperity. <hi>O Lord I pray thee now geue proſperi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty</hi> vnto Elizabeth, béeing ſafely couched vnder the ſhadow of thy winges, proſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per thou her, O Lord, proſper thou the counſailes of her hart, proſper thou the woorks of her hands: yea O Lord, what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer ſhee taketh in hand, let it proſper in thy ſight: yea and ſo proſper her, O Lord, in the gouernment of vs thy peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple committed vnto her charge, as that we alſo may proſper vnder her: and that as in all worldly proſperity, ſo princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pally in all godlines and honeſty: yea <hi>Now,</hi> O Lord, geue proſperity vnto her, as thou haſt hetherto proſpered her gouernment aboue al other Kinges and Princes of the earth, to the terror of thy enemies, to the comfort of thy choſen, to the admiration of all men: ſo, O Lord, geue now, yea and euer proſperity vnto Elizabeth. Thus ought we (dearly belo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued)
<pb facs="tcp:11157:28"/> in the middeſt of our reioycing to mixe prayer vnto God for the ſafety and proſperity of Queen Elizabeth: great is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> force of prayer before God: it pearceth the clowds, and aſſendeth into the eares of the Almighty: and although the Lord heareth not ſinners, <hi>Iohn.</hi> 9. But their <note place="margin">Iohn. 9.</note> prayer is turned into ſin: yet the prayer of the righteous, is euen as the ſweet incenſe and as the euening ſacrifice moſt pleaſant and delectable in his ſight: ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing this promiſe, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> whatſoeuer they ſhal aſke, they ſhal obtaine it, yea great is the force of the prayer of one righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous man, if it be feruent, as <hi>Iames</hi> ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth <hi>cap.</hi> 5. And then how much more <note place="margin">Iames. 5.</note> forceable is the prayer of the whole con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> righteous being aſſembled together before him in his houſe, which is the houſe of prayer. Wherefore now being aſſembled together at this time, vpon this occaſion into this place: yea &amp; at what time ſoeuer, vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> any other occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> we aſſemble our ſelues together into y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Church of God (that I ſpeake nothing of priuate prayer in all places) lifting vp cleane handes and purifyed hartes, let vs pray. <hi>O Lord, I pray thee, ſaue</hi>
                  <pb facs="tcp:11157:29"/> 
                  <hi>now. O Lord I pray thee now geue proſperity</hi> vnto Elizabeth: For as this is the duty of all men one towards ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, but principally of ſubiects towards their Kinges and Princes, to commend the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in their prayers vnto God. 1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 2 <note place="margin">1 Tim. 2.</note> ſo yet chiefly it ſtandeth vs vpon, which are y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſubiectes of this Common-wealth to pray for the ſafety &amp; proſperity of our Queene Elizabeth: for in the ſafety of Elizabeth conſiſteth ours: in her peace, ours: in her proſperity, ours: in her life, ours: in her death, ours: in her deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, ours: If the Lord either by timely or vntimely, either by naturall or vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naturall death ſhould take away Eliza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beth from Engla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, it would indeed be a ioyful and happy Elizabeth, but a moſt woefull and miſerable England. God graunt mine eies neuer ſee, nor mine eares neuer heare of the death of Eliza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beth: Wherefore, <hi>O Lord, I pray thee ſaue now: O Lord, I pray thee geue now proſperity</hi> vnto Elizabeth: and let all thoſe which entirely loue Eliza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beth, ſay, So be it.</p>
               <p n="3">3 <hi>A bleſſing, verſe. 26. Bleſſed is he that commeth in the name of the</hi>
                  <pb facs="tcp:11157:29"/> 
                  <hi>Lord: we haue bleſſed you out of the houſe of</hi> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 
                  <hi>Lord.</hi> Which words, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> moſt vſuall tranſlations do ſet downe after the forme and maner of wiſhing or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiring. <hi>Bleſſed be hee, &amp;c.</hi> As if the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple had prayed vnto the Lord to bleſſe Dauid their King. But the moſt appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued tranſlatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> according to the Hebrew ſet them downe by way of affirmation, <hi>Bleſſed is hee, &amp;c.</hi> Wherin the people do affirme Dauid their King to bee the bleſſed of the Lord. <hi>Bleſſed is Dauid.</hi> the which they confirme by two notable arguments. Firſt Dauid commeth in the name of the Lord, that is, Dauid commeth to rule and gouerne the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth. Hee obtaineth the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, not in his owne name, but in the name of the Lord: not thruſting himſelf thereunto, but hauing the ſame thruſt vpon him by the Lord: not vſurpingly aduauncing himſelfe, but beeing mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culouſly thereunto aduaunced by the Lord: and therefore Dauid is bleſſed: for as they which come in their owne names are curſed: ſo they which come in the name of the Lord are bleſſed: but Dauid commeth in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> name of the Lord,
<pb facs="tcp:11157:30"/> therfore Dauid is bleſſed. Seco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dly Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid is bleſſed of them that are of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> houſe of the Lord: that is, either of the prieſts of the Lordes houſe, of his Sanctuary, whoſe office it was to bleſſe, as appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth <hi>Num.</hi> 6. and alſo <hi>Deut.</hi> 10. or elſe <note place="margin">Num. 6. Deut. 10.</note> more generally eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of all thoſe that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long to the houſe of the Lord, that is, which purely woorſhippe him in his Sanctuary, in Sion: And therefore Dauid is bleſſed of the Lord: for the Lord mercifully ratifyeth, and confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth the bleſſinges of his Church: hee bleſſeth thoſe whom his Church bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth: and hee curſeth thoſe whom his Church curſeth. But his Church e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen the Congregation of his choſen Children, beeyng bleſſed by Dauid: haue bleſſed Dauid: and therefore Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid is bleſſed of the Lord: Lo how in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uincibly they haue prooued that Dauid is bleſſed. The conſideration whereof could not but much confirme the hope of the ſafety and proſperity of Dauid, for which they prayed before: for not onely ſafety, and proſperity, but euen all good thinges follow the bleſſing of God. The Lords bleſſing is no vaine
<pb facs="tcp:11157:30"/> nor naked bleſſing, as is oftentimes the bleſſing of man: But al good things are heape<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d vpon thoſe which are bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed of the Lord: Let Shemei there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore curſe Dauid. 2. <hi>Sam.</hi> 16. yet Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid is bleſſed: yea let the enemies of <note place="margin">2. Sam. 16.</note> Dauid conſpire together againſt him: yet ſhall the Lord geue ſafety and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperity vnto Dauid, becauſe hee is the bleſſed of the Lord.</p>
               <p>In like ſorte, (dearely beloued) this can not but bee vnto a ſinguler comfort and conſolation continuing our hope of the ſafetie and proſperitie of our gracious Quéene Elizabeth, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe ſhe is the bleſſed of the Lord. E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lizabeth is the bleſſed of the Lord, and therefore let her enimies curſe her with booke, bell and candle, the curſe ſhall not fal vpon her, but ſhe is bleſſed, yea &amp; ſhall be bleſſed for euer: for there is no repentance in the Lord: God is not as man, that hee ſhould lye, nor as the ſonne of man that he ſhould repent: hath he ſaid, and ſhall he not doe it? and hath he ſpoken, and ſhall he not accompliſh it? hath he bleſſed, and ſhall he not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue his bleſſing? yes ſurely, with him
<pb facs="tcp:11157:31"/> there is no variableneſſe, neither ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow of chaunging, <hi>Iames.</hi> 1. If Iſaac <note place="margin">Iam. 1.</note> was conſtant in his bleſſing vnwit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tingly beſtowed vpon Iacob, and not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding all the teares of Eſau, would not call backe the ſame, but con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed it, ſaying: I haue bleſſed him, and therefore he ſhall be bleſſed: <hi>Gen.</hi> 27. Then how much more conſtant <note place="margin">Gen. 27.</note> ſhall the Lorde bee in continuing his bleſſing vpon thoſe his children whom he hath once not vnwittingly but wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly bleſſed, notwithſtanding all the teares, outcries, curſings, and bannings of the vngodly? ſaying, I haue bleſſed them, therefore they ſhall bee bleſſed. And if the Lord bleſſe, who ſhall curſe? How ſhal I curſe, where the Lord hath not curſed (ſaith Balaam to Balaac) or how ſhall I deteſt where the Lorde hath not deteſted? or if they curſe, or deteſt thoſe whom the Lorde bleſſeth, and reioyceth in: their curſing ſhall fall vpon them ſelues: as the Prophet Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid ſaith, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 109. As they loued cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing, ſo ſhal it come vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: as they lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued <note place="margin">Pſal. 109.</note> not bleſſing, ſo it ſhal be far off from them: as they clothed themſelues with
<pb facs="tcp:11157:31"/> curſing: as with a garment, ſo it ſhall come into their bowels like water, and like oyle into their bones. But y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> bleſſed of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lord, ſhal be bleſſed for euer. That Elizabeth is the bleſſed of the Lord, I proue eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by the ſelfe ſame arguments wherby the bleſſednes of Dauid is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed in this place. Firſt, <hi>Beſſed is he that co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth in the name of the Lord,</hi> but Elizabeth commeth in the name of the Lord: ſhe came not to gouerne this land in her own name, but in the name of the Lord: ſhe obtained not the crown by her own power, but by the power of the Lord, who miraculouſly aduanced her thereunto, &amp; no leſſe miraculouſily hath hetherto vpheld her therin: &amp; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore this is an euident teſtimonie y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſhe is the bleſſed &amp; beloued of the Lord. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, <hi>She is bleſſed out of the houſe of the Lord,</hi> as it hath béene bleſſed by her, ſo it bleſſeth her amongſt all the mightie kings and princes of the earth, there is none by whom the houſe of the Lord, the Church of Chriſt hath béene ſo wonderfully bleſſed, as it hath béene by Quéene Elizabeth at this day: by her principally it is that the kingdom of
<pb facs="tcp:11157:32"/> Antechriſt decayeth dayly: by her prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipally it is, that the Church of Chriſt within theſe few yeares in ſo many na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions is augmented and aduanced: by her it is that the baniſhed children of Chriſt, not hauing a place where to reſt their heades, are louingly receaued, and carefully fed and nouriſhed: by her it is that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> oppreſſed ones are defended: &amp; they which war for it, are ſtre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gthned, and therfore woorthely hath ſhe deſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued the euerlaſting bleſſing of the houſe of the Lord: yea and no doubt, the whole houſe of the Lord doth bleſſe her. And therefore wee may alſo aſſure our ſelues, that the Lord ratifying and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firming the bleſſing of his Church, bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth her. The conſideration whereof, (dearly beloued) as I ſaid before can not but greatly comfort and confirme the certainty of our hope, concerning the ſafety and proſperity of our moſt graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Soueraigne, Queene Elizabeth, that notwithſtanding, ſhee is curſed by the Pope, the maiſter of miſrule, and author of all miſchiefe: and be hated of all his fauourers who with all their powers bend themſelues againſt her to
<pb facs="tcp:11157:32"/> ſubdue her, and bring her to confuſion: yet that they ſhall not bee able to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaile ouer her: but that the Lord for his names ſake: who hath miraculouſly ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaunced her, and hetherto preſerued her: yea and for his Church ſake, which béeing bleſſed by her, hath bleſſed her, he will geue ſafety and proſperity vnto E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lizabeth, to the continuance of the glory of his name, and the encreaſing of the bleſſednes of his Church by her. The which the Lord vouchſafe to graunt for his Sonne Chriſt his ſake, the head of his Church. To whom with the holy Ghoſt, three diſtinct perſons, and one onely God, bee rendred all honour and praiſe, both now and for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer.</p>
               <closer>Amen.</closer>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
